<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="part">Mattheson: Der Ober-Classe dreizehntes Probstück (english translation)</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Niels Pfeffer</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Mattheson.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="0" type="chapter">
      <head>Annotations.</head>
      <div n="1">
        <head>§. 1.</head>
        <p xml:id="p1-1">
          Everything in nature desires for pleasant variation and never-ending diversion.
          But no other science embodies this for a greater extent than music. Now I cannot tell,
          whether for this reason the academies in Great Britains came up with giving
          a strangely colourful, ornamented and multicoloured rope like the one of
          Joseph to their doctors and professors of music but not to all the other graduates.
          But in this school it was necessary to do a little variation in the present piece
          after having covered quite a distance of troublesome keys.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="2">
        <head>§. 2.</head>
        <p xml:id="p2-1">
          Although one could have put everything neatly in a 9/8 signature and write
          an "Allegro" above, it cannot do harm to write a 9/16 signature in order to do a favour
          for those who have perhaps never seen it, or at least seldomly, and who are therefore
          slightly scared when encountering it. They say that <hi rendition="#b">one shall not
          unnecessarily augment or double what belongs to a science</hi>.
          That old and honourable musician did not say wrongly that <hi rendition="#b">it is a
          great folly to turn a melody that can be written in simple and plain notes
          dubious by using obscure signatures.</hi>, as the <hi rendition="#aq"><foreign xml:lang="ita">Cantor</foreign></hi> of
          Schwa&#x0364;bisch Hall, <persName corresp="#ed_esw_kxx_qlb">mister Majer</persName> wisely says in his
          <hi rendition="#aq"><bibl corresp="#ed_tyg_hdl_tlb">Hodego Musico, p. 28</bibl></hi>. Yet one has to use quick signatures and
          quick notes in order to correctly express quick music, so that signature and
          music do match. Secondly one must not reject the fashion in certain pieces,
          which otherwise is called <hi rendition="#b">to swim against the stream</hi>. And (3) no obscure
          signatures will occur here.<note place="foot" n="(*)" type="footnote" xml:id="footnote1">The signatures
          2/4, 2/8 and 2 are not obscure at all but very simple and natural and those
          who think one could use instead the common C alone, are wrong, they have no
          experience and they do not know how to differentiate the movements</note>.
          The appearance of a musical piece is often seductive. Just as some thorough-bass
          appears to be simple while it is not, there are as well
          sometimes basses that appear colourful
          while indeed not being dangerous: this on one of them.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="3">
        <head>§. 3.</head>
        <p xml:id="p3-1">
          The <ref target="#measure-0000001263987989">eleventh measure</ref>
          has to mean something since the bass is resting. Meanwhile
          something can go on the right hand, for example in this imitative
          way:
        </p>
        <notatedMusic xml:id="music-example1">
          <ptr target="music-example1.xml" />
        </notatedMusic>
        <p xml:id="p3-2">
          Which one also should be told in the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000401264624">13th measure.</ref>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="4">
        <head>§. 4.</head>
        <p xml:id="p4-1">
          From the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000398572267">nineteenth measure</ref>
          until the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000135352827">first repetition sign</ref>
          the bass indicates already that the right hand can make use of the bass' preceding
          progressions, about which to lose more words is not necessary.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="5">
        <head>§. 5.</head>
        <p xml:id="p5-1">
          Since in the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000720476607">eighth measure of the second section</ref>
          the bass suggests an alternation, one has to force the right hand to do a little syncopation
          once more. In order that it does not happen always in only one way, one can
          do it one measure from below and in the other from above and alternate it
          measure-wise, just like in the bass itself, as you can clearly see from the
          following example:
        </p>
        <notatedMusic xml:id="music-example2">
          <ptr target="music-example2.xml" />
        </notatedMusic>
      </div>

      <div n="6">
        <head>§. 6.</head>
        <p xml:id="p6-2">
          <ref target="#measure-0000001692641009">The tenth</ref> and
          <ref target="#measure-0000000980772493">eleventh measure</ref>
          can be treated according to the previous instruction. But in the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000813644631">twelfth</ref> one has to pay attention
          to all the chord, primarily so that the arpeggiation does not occur in thirds
          which is too narrow, as already mentioned. Secondly one needs to take care that
          the three-part harmony is perfect in all regards since, when observing both those
          pieces, it cannot be another way than that the syncopation from below always
          starts with the chord's fifth, while the one from above starts with the third. Both
          those types are called <hi rendition="#aq"><foreign xml:lang="">Syzygiam remotam</foreign></hi>, meaning that the
          notes of a chord are somewhat more apart. But when two chords follow each other
          step-wise, up- or downwards, and both begin with fifths, it would be a mistake.
          For that reason the described alternation is the means of choice in order to
          avoid mistakes. Even though there are no consecutive chords in
          step-wise motion in this test piece, I will demonstrate this case and illustrate once
          more what it means to alternate in the fifth and the third.
        </p>
        <notatedMusic xml:id="music-example3">
          <ptr target="music-example3.xml" />
        </notatedMusic>
      </div>

      <div n="7">
        <head>§. 7.</head>
        <p xml:id="p7-1">
          When the bass has a clause like in the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000663286333">13th</ref> and
          <ref target="#measure-0000000999021806">14th measure</ref>
          that consists of two measures before being repeated, the alternation is not
          done measure-wise but in two measures or more depending on the length of
          the motive. On the two consecutively jumping chords in the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000815808309">17th measure</ref>
          one has to alternate.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="8">
        <head>§. 8.</head>
        <p xml:id="p8-1">
          From
          <ref target="#measure-0000000815808309">measure 18</ref> until the end
          both hands should do a simultaneous arpeggiation, which has a great effect,
          when beginning and the right place. It happens in the following way. The
          eight last bars are fully written out here:
        </p>
        <notatedMusic xml:id="music-example4">
          <ptr target="music-example4.xml" />
        </notatedMusic>
      </div>

      <div n="9">
        <head>§. 9.</head>
        <p xml:id="p9-1">
          Although this arpeggio appears to be in two voices, is basically in four voices
          and in a quick tempo it sounds even more full than normally eight voices
          as straight-forward and plain chords. But one shall never play it except where
          the bass is alone or where the music is strong.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
