<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/basisformat_customized.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="part">Mattheson: Der Ober-Classe neunzehntes Probstück (english translation)</title>
        <editor role="translator">
          <persName xml:id="pfeffer">
            <surname>Niels</surname>
            <forename>Pfeffer</forename>
          </persName>
        </editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
          <persName>
            <surname>Niels</surname>
            <forename>Pfeffer</forename>
          </persName>
        </publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
            <p>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is an original digital text.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="0" type="chapter">
      <head>Annotations.</head>
      <div n="1">
        <head>§. 1.</head>
        <p>
          Beating the time might be somewhat necessary here, especially for someone
          who is not sitting firmly in the saddle. But I doubt whether such
          a person would want to beat the time himself or rather have the beat given
          to him. In my opinion, the latter would be the best, so that the
          rest could be done with more attention. In the meantime, a master
          needs neither the one nor the other when he plays alone and yet
          he may not stumble if he is not to be booed at.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="2">
        <head>§. 2.</head>
        <p>
          In those places of this piece where the 6 is so frequent, as if it were
          the place where they all had a rendezvous, one can, especially with two-tailed
          notes, either use the sixth alone or the third: but in such a way that when
          the sixth plays the fast notes, the third is not lacking, but lying;
          and vice versa, where the thirds are going along, the sixth must also
          be present in the hand. But at which places the sixths follow each other
          and at which the third can do so, I will elaborate.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="3">
        <head>§. 3.</head>
        <p>
          In the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000533608303 #measure-0000001856501508">second and third measure</ref>
          sixths do the job while the f# is kept as the third to d,
          which then becomes a fourth to c# and therefore nothing unpleasant, but something decent.
          In the
          <ref target="#measure-0000001184386067 #measure-0000001578689986">ninth and tenth measure</ref>,
          on the other hand, the third takes on and
          leaves the sixth alone, which would sound bad to the f# if they were slower notes;
          but since they pass quickly, and finally everything stops at the third, nothing bad
          can happen to the ears. In the other case, however, the sixth makes a
          pleasant-sounding fifth with the notes in between.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="4">
        <head>§. 4.</head>
        <p>
          Whenever a measure begins with a rest, namely with an eighth,
          nothing is given to the following note and nothing in advance either.
          However, I want to exclude the beginning from this, and I am
          only talking about the occurrences in the
          <ref target="#rest-0000001531580152 #rest-0000001496543014 #rest-0000001713253157 #rest-0000001164364404 #rest-0000000844719707 #rest-0000001933121666 #rest-0000001173989907 #rest-0000001822354377 #rest-0000001679602312 #rest-0000001197851580 #rest-0000000964463351 #rest-0000000542946318 #rest-0000001539491416 #rest-0000002011106610 #rest-0000000875827094 #rest-0000001099723409">
          7th, 8th, 12th, 19th, 20th, 21st, 28th, 29th, 30th, 31st, 32nd, 41st, 44th, 45th, 46th
          and 52nd measure</ref>. Now, in all of these places, the measure
          does not begin exactly with the rest, but the point is that
          nothing may be played on the note that
          follows the rest: because it goes through, it has
          little special meaning, and after the breaking off
          <note type="editorial" resp="#pfeffer">i.e. interruption by the rest</note>
          only serves as a hook, so to speak, by which one thing is attached to another.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="5">
        <head>§. 5.</head>
        <p>
          In the <ref target="#measure-0000001060551138">fifteenth measure</ref>,
          the sixths prevail and the thirds remain lying.
          In the <ref target="#measure-0000001367850118">23rd measure</ref>, an ornament comes
          to mind that can be used quite often
          in the left hand, all the more so because usually a great lack
          of ornamented playing (as there are: good sharp trills, appoggiaturas, accents, etc.)
          can be perceived in thorough-bass playing.
          What I am asking here concerns the leap into the third upward, where one can
          make a strong slide (Schleifer) in most cases, and thereby give
          the high note an immense strength. However, such a slide must not
          be drawn out as in singing, but rather made short and somewhat
          forceful, just as if one were to place the three fingers at the same
          time, and only lift one after the other. It can be better shown by playing
          than by describing it.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="6">
        <head>§. 6.</head>
        <p>
          In the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000452779095 #measure-0000002077720718">34th and 35th measure</ref>,
          one might wonder where the harsh figures
          are coming from; however, it is the sixth and the chord to the
          following notes that are only taken in advance. Everyone can easily
          recognize the transitus irregularis or the cambiata here. To be sure,
          they will seem somewhat strange to some in the downbeat of the measure;
          but as long as it is said in the Hohe Schule der musicalischen Composition, p. 84:
          To introduce the note cambiate on the first beat of the measure
          is very seldom permitted, so long will I also make use of this very
          seldom here, and believe that this exception, in the case of a highly
          mobile mensur, can pass as regular, if one makes use of it very seldom.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="7">
        <head>§. 7.</head>
        <p>
          If one can play a few notes in canon with the right hand in the
          <ref target="#measure-0000001126576291">41st measure</ref>,
          and let the bass follow, it will not sound bad.
          Otherwise, there is little more to remember that is not
          related to what has already been said. 
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="8">
        <head>§. 8.</head>
        <p>
          Mr. St. Lambert calls this tone p. 29. F ut Fa Dieze Mineur, and writes:
          Rare. F# minor is shorter, and in my case nothing rare.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
