<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/basisformat_customized.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="part">Mattheson: Der Ober-Classe zwanzigstes Probstück (english translation)</title>
        <editor role="translator">
          <persName xml:id="pfeffer">
            <surname>Niels</surname>
            <forename>Pfeffer</forename>
          </persName>
        </editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
          <persName>
            <surname>Niels</surname>
            <forename>Pfeffer</forename>
          </persName>
        </publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
            <p>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is an original digital text.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="0" type="chapter">
      <head>Annotations</head>
      <div n="1">
        <head>§. 1.</head>
        <p>
          Whoever can jump firmly here will do well, but
          another will often stumble, trip or hit the wrong keys.
          At the end of the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000174603578">fourth measure</ref>, one would like
          to arpeggiate a little, and then to play in the
          <ref target="#measure-0000001411700064 #measure-0000000264878814 #measure-0000000328043882">fifth, sixth and
          seventh measure</ref> in this way:
          <notatedMusic>
            <ptr target="music-example1.xml"/>
          </notatedMusic>
          This will also be convenient in the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000567414890 #measure-0000000493851592 #measure-0000001346110271">fifteenth,
          sixteenth and seventeenth measure.</ref>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="2">
        <head>§. 2.</head>
        <p>
          <ref target="#note-0000001444913642 #note-0000001182642635">On the two eighth notes</ref>
          at the end of the eighth measure, the
          right hand plays these following notes, and imitates it
          in the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000566982188 #measure-0000000362882873 #measure-0000000785009598">ninth, tenth and eleventh measure</ref>
          according to the bass.
          <notatedMusic>
            <ptr target="music-example2.xml"/>
          </notatedMusic>
          In the
          <ref target="#measure-0000001425906512 #measure-0000000763300727">18th and 19th measure</ref>
          the same manner occurs again. 
          But one who does not want to lag behind in the
          <ref target="#measure-0000001527420734">20th</ref> and
          following measures, may not hesitate long, but has to let the fingers gallop.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="3">
        <head>§. 3.</head>
        <p>
          Since the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000091997873">second part begins with a specific arpeggio</ref>,
          it implies that the right hand should consequently seek
          the opportunity to imitate it. This can be done
          right away in the <ref target="#measure-0000001923958404">second measure</ref> as follows –
          <notatedMusic>
            <ptr target="music-example3.xml"/>
          </notatedMusic>
            – while not forgetting that the bass notes
            may go along in octaves and thus add gravity.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="4">
        <head>§. 4.</head>
        <p>
          In the
          <ref target="#measure-0000001018439983 #measure-0000001374019244">fifth and sixth measure of the second part</ref>,
          the imitation described above is again taken into account, and if one wants
          to let thirds go along in the <ref target="#measure-0000001269146673">seventh measure</ref> in the treble
          it fills out better than plain chords. Thus, in the
          <ref target="#measure-0000001902655465 #measure-0000000766995769 #measure-0000001822556232">ninth,
          tenth and eleventh measure</ref> the above arpeggio must be repeated,
          and only this must be played on the last
          four notes of the eleventh measure: 
          <notatedMusic>
            <ptr target="music-example4.xml"/>
          </notatedMusic>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="5">
        <head>§. 5.</head>
        <p>
           Nor can it sound bad if at the end of the
           <ref target="#measure-0000000216610351">fourth measure</ref>
           the right hand arpeggiates its chords in the same way
          the bass arpeggiates its own. However, this shall only
           be done on these three quarters:
          <notatedMusic>
            <ptr target="music-example5.xml"/>
          </notatedMusic>
          That the last notes take octaves with the bass
          is done with on porpuse in order to express the
          main theme, which reappears there, all the more clearly;
          but where the same notes occur again, they must not
          be played again with octaves, but in the usual way,
          like the rest, so that it varies. 
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="6">
        <head>§. 6.</head>
        <p>
           Right after, where the bass remains still,
           the right hand can emerge just with a broken chord
           and what is figured. For example: 
          <notatedMusic>
            <ptr target="music-example6.xml"/>
          </notatedMusic>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="7">
        <head>§. 7.</head>
        <p>
          In the same way, the <ref target="#measure-0000002005099252">18th measure</ref>
          can easily let the right hand proceed in harmony
          with the left hand in the just prepared manner.
          <ref target="#clef-0000000962308835">At the beginning of the low bass clef</ref>, however,
          one plays only on every fourth note, and where
          the bass moves in quarters, this variation is played in the discant: 
          <notatedMusic xml:id="music-example7" facs="#facsZone-music-example7">
            <ptr target="music-example7.xml"/>
          </notatedMusic>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="8">
        <head>§. 8.</head>
        <p>
          That this key must be something rare in France can be
          seen from St. Lambert's book on thorough-bass, where it
          reads as follows:
          <note place="foot" n="*)"><foreign xml:lang="fra">Le B Fa Si Beccarre
          etant un Ton, sur lequel on compose rarement, il n'y a point
          de modulation qui lui soit particulierement affectée: s'il en avoit une, ce croit la mineure.</foreign>
          <bibl><persName corresp="#ed_dwf_j5x_qlb">Mr. de St. Lambert</persName>, Traité de l'Accompagnement,
          p.27.</bibl></note>
          "B is a key in which one rarely composes. There is no third which is particularly associated with it,
          but if it had one, it would probably be the minor third." 
          Nevertheless, we know that its nature is minor and not major;
          I have already shown the reasons for this in the second Orchestre book.
          And that this tone is nothing rare for us is shown by countless
          examples that are found daily. There are things with trumpets
          and timpani in B minor, which might seem strange to some;
          but if he were to hear the mobile<note>beweglich</note> chorale: Ach bleibe bei uns, Herr Jesu Christ, etc.,
          where the singing voices are set in the chamber tone B, and in the modulation into the D major,
          are accompanied with the above heroic instruments chorus tone, only once,
          well performed, it would go to his heart.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
