<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Mattheson: Der Ober-Classe Sechzehntes Probstück (english translation)</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
          <persName>
            <surname>Pfeffer</surname>
            <forename>Niels</forename>
          </persName>
        </publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
            <p>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Mattheson.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="0" type="chapter">
      <head>Annotations</head>
      <div n="1">
        <head>§ 1.</head>
        <p>
          The present key was notated differently
          in the middle class of this <hi rendition="#i">Grosse General-Baß-Schule</hi>
          than here, despite them being (in the common disposition of the keyboard instruments)
          the same tangent. It is well-consideredly written <emph>according to the
          common disposition of our keyboards</emph>: for it was sufficently
          proven mathematically by others, that the key <emph>♯G</emph> is generally very different
          from <emph>♭A</emph>. I add that it could be put in a more natural way, for
          the characterstics if the first key requires a minor third and therefore
          is essentially minor, while the other naturally needs the
          major third, and therefore is major by nature, which cannot
          be the same key at the same time. The harmonic reasons are not yet
          known, but in praxi this proposition is true.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="2">
        <head>§ 2.</head>
        <p>
          For a long time it has been well noticed that the so-called
          semitones contain an ambiguity, as it were; namely, that ♯C is
          a different thing in itself than ♭D; that ♯D should be distinguished
          from ♭E; that ♯E does not have anything in common with the ordinary f. 
          They have quite rightly proven that ♯F is not ♭G; that ♭A and ♯G
          are not basically the same; that ♭H means something quite different
          from ♯A, and that finally ♯H can have no relationship to the ordinary
          C: for therein consists a piece of the enharmonic octave, on which the
          introduction, or Unterclasse, has eloberated extensively. 
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="3">
        <head>§ 3.</head>
        <p>
           However, our improvers have not yet gone so far as to
           distinguish C from ♯B and not to mix ♭F with E, or that,
           just as C and f can be notated in different ways,
           the same, if improper adjacent steps <!-- ? -->
           at least require different signs:
           which is, however, highly necessary especially
           in those kinds of keys that hiddenly modulate into
           enharmonic regions, which is why it will be discussed 
           amongst other things in the conclusion of this work
           and it will also be pointed out, which other inconvenience
           in notation arises from it.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="4">
        <head>§ 4.</head>
        <p xml:id="p4-1">
          Our ancestors, as they made their remarks about
          the lack of tones and were of the opinion that the
          Clavier still lacked seven keys in each octave
          in the semitones, would hardly have thought that
          after their time, one would ever compose a piece from
          such divided steps (let alone from their breaks), <!-- ? -->
          especially since Capricornus and Bernhard already
          invested in this and considered it almost impossible
          that it could be driven further; as is evident: they have
          only considered the sequences or modulations of the other
          common tones, and according to such basic theorem, have
          assumed their annotations to be indisputable and indispensable:
          which is nevertheless a mistake. 
        </p>

      </div>

      <div n="5">
        <head>§ 5.</head>
        <p xml:id="p5-1">
          As little as we may believe that something might show up in ♯E,
          in so far as it is different from F, it can happen just as easily;
          and I do not want to be a guarantor for this, nor do I want
          to demand that one shall make special, fundamental changes in the
          instrument because of it, since they do not help;
          my thoughts go with all modesty to the effect that only those signs
          should be used, by which such things can be noted properly,
          mainly because of the mentioned consequences. For we must
          abandon the hope of improving the Clavier, of augmenting it, and
          of bringing it to perfection, and be content instead with a good
          temperament: because, in spite of manifold suggestions
          and attempts, a patchwork of keys does not mean anything;
          but to express my standpoint through in music should not do any harm:
          and even that we cannot do properly, as will be shown in the last
          Probstück of this class and indeed in the immediately following aria.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="6">
        <head>§ 6.</head>
        <p>
          The little which remains to be noted is that from
          the <ref target="#measure-0000001123115174">5th measure of this piece</ref> to the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000741277401">third measure of the last part</ref>, then again from the
          <ref target="#measure-0000001490618817">10th</ref> of said part to the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000205329913">17th</ref>, everything can be
          played in the right hand in a decent manner,
          but where the 6/4 occurs, a graceful arpeggiation can be applied;
          besides, it does not require any major skill.
        </p>

        <p>
          <emph>ARIA.</emph>
          <notatedMusic xml:id="aria-inquelseno">
            <ptr target="aria-inquelseno.xml" />
          </notatedMusic>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="7">
        <head>§ 7.</head>
        <p>
          I found this aria with a noble person who came here from Italy, not knowing who its composer was.
          One can tell that it must have been composed either for a castrato or
          for someone who sang in a high alto, also that some instruments belong to it, which I, however,
          have considered unnecessary here, as well as several inserted rests.
          The intention now is to give an example from daily practice where the G-sharp minor
          is used strongly, and for this I take what falls into my hands first, as it were by chance.
          That, however, G-sharp minor strikes more often than A-flat major is true,
          because the first has the minor third essentially, the other only accidentally -
          yet it is the same in playing, only the latter can be notatated more purely,
          which is why it was chosen here for the Probstück. However, I find a beautiful
          movement in A-flat major in Mossi's work, p. 34, which I would like to note,
          because it did not occur to me in the twelfth Probstück of this class.
          Another movement, however, from the G-sharp major is found by the
          same composer on p. 59, which proves my above remarks. The work
          mentioned here, and presented as an example, consists of twelve sonatas
          with a violin and bass, engraved in copper in Amsterdam, and the author's
          name is Giovanni Mossi. 
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="8">
        <head>§ 8.</head>
        <p>
          At the end of the preceding explanation, I said that this aria was
          intended to show that we cannot always express well our views
          with notes, and that we indeed lack signs when we want to play
          into the unfamiliar tones. This is especially clear from the
          last two lines of the above aria, since a note occurs there 
          five times in both, voice and bass, which has a double cross
          (♯♯) in front of it and signifies a so-called g, which I, however,
          consider (although it is the usual notation) to be a defect,
          and at the end of this work I will present my reasons and means,
          as much as I understand them and have them available, along with more examples. 
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
