<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/basisformat_customized.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="part">Mattheson: Der Ober-Classe achtzehntes Probstück (english translation)</title>
        <editor role="translator">
          <persName xml:id="pfeffer">
            <surname>Niels</surname>
            <forename>Pfeffer</forename>
          </persName>
        </editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
          <persName>
            <surname>Niels</surname>
            <forename>Pfeffer</forename>
          </persName>
        </publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
            <p>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is an original digital text.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="0" type="chapter">
      <head>Annotations</head>
      <div n="1">
        <head>§. 1.</head>
        <p>
          In the first measure, one plays only on the
          <ref target="#note-0000001037330976 #note-0000000662175992">first two notes</ref>,
          but not on the other.
          In the second measure, one plays on no note
          <ref target="#note-0000000526111068">except the first</ref>,
          <ref target="#note-0000001535338502">likewise in the third measure</ref>, 
          but in the fourth measure again
          <ref target="#note-0000002101406706 #note-0000000282639984">on the first two notes</ref>.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="2">
        <head>§. 2.</head>
        <p>
          In the fifth measure, only the <ref target="#note-0000000316164270 #note-0000000125245410">first and eighth note</ref>
          are played with the appropriate and specified chord.
          The same applies for the <ref target="#note-0000000667394726 #note-0000000276020849">sixth measure</ref>.
          In the seventh measure, it must be noted that the 6 above
          the <ref target="#note-0000001776178721">last note</ref> must already be struck and anticipated with the preceding
          <ref target="#note-0000001054477391">b</ref>.
          In the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000396295556">eighth bar,</ref>
          the right hand does with the F# and B that which the bass played
          at the beginning with B and E.
          In the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000359208733">ninth measure</ref>,
          this continues with B and G# to E and with B and F# to D#.
          In the
          <ref target="#measure-0000002097787176">tenth</ref> it is the same as in the fifth.
          <ref target="#measure-0000001047849544">In the eleventh</ref>, however, the right
          hand takes the subject and begins with e C#, then e B, then e A, then e G#, and finally e F#,
          just as the first four bars of the Prob-Stück read note for note.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="3">
        <head>§. 3.</head>
        <p>
          With the following
          <ref target="#measure-0000000404998919 #measure-0000000797194466 #measure-0000000971045622">measures 16, 17 and 18</ref>
          one proceeds as with the fifth measure.
          Where the transposition of the theme begins with the
          <ref target="#clef-0000001087880551">tenor clef</ref>,
          one proceeds just as with the beginning. In the <ref target="#measure-0000001099786812">28th measure</ref>,
          it is to be noted that the right hand goes along in thirds with each note
          in addition to the sixth, which remains lying. Further, the 37th
          and <ref target="#measure-0000000804701007">38th measures</ref> are to be taken into consideration, where one plays
          exactly what the bass has had in the two preceding measures, however, as if a lower treble clef
          were now in front of it. The
          <ref target="#measure-0000001280575648 #measure-0000001343838691 #measure-0000001748474312 #measure-0000000023982366">next four measures</ref>
          up to the end of the first part are played quite strongly with chords on every note
          and full-voiced.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="4">
        <head>§. 4.</head>
        <p>
          It can be observed that in the
          <ref target="#measure-0000001612761976">second measure of the second part</ref>,
          the first note passes through, which rarely happens and depends on the judgment,
          since one must observe on which note the emphasis or accent falls, which
          here does not happen on the first, but on the second note, because the latter is
          the last which rises and it is at the same time the beginning of a new progression.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="5">
        <head>§. 5.</head>
        <p>
          Up to the <ref target="#measure-0000000931339172">27th measure of this part</ref>,
          there is nothing further to explain or elucidate.
          Here, the first subject must be placed and developed again, first with
          f# c#, then with f# and d# to B, then with f# c# again to Bb, and finally with f# b, as the
          seventh to G#, which is resolved with f and b. The first subject must be placed and performed here again.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="6">
        <head>§. 6.</head>
        <p>
          In the
          <ref target="#measure-0000000030851495">31st measure</ref>,
          the material from
          <ref target="#measure-0000002093783867">measure 37</ref> of the first part occurs again,
          although with other notes, so that here one has nothing more to do than
          to play with the right hand the same notes that the bass played before,
          but in the previous manner, as if a low treble clef were in front of it.
          The following four or five measures can easily be played in thirds,
          and finally, the conclusion is made again with a transposition of
          the subject in the right hand as follows:
          
          <notatedMusic xml:id="music-example1">
            <ptr target="music-example1.xml"/>
          </notatedMusic>

           However, the left hand must play everything as full-voiced as possible, 
           which is set now and forever.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="7">
        <head>§. 7.</head>
        <p>
          I have diligently wanted to place the whole passage here,
          so that, if in the previous descriptions some things might sometimes
          seem obscure to one or the other, it will all be illustrated and
          made clearer from this example; since it remains the case that whoever
          is knowledgeable about a matter is naturally not so adept at presenting
          it as is often necessary for an uninformed person; therefore, no one can
          be too comprehensible in teaching, so that even a little prolixity and
          repetition is not immediately to be blamed, as long as its intention is 
          directed to clarity.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="8">
        <head>§. 8.</head>
        <p>
          The famous Mr. Telemann once published six concertos, and had them
          engraved very neatly in copper, which the then Serene Prince Ernst of Saxony-Weimar
          composed with his own hand and from his own invention: in these
          the Concerto V. is in the above key, and it is one of the most beautiful.
          Besides, to find free lords who compose music and who can be mentioned
          is something that does not occur every day, but it gives
          a peculiar advantage to the precious music.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
