<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/basisformat_customized.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="part">Mattheson: Der Ober-Classe siebenzehntes Probstück (english translation)</title>
        <editor role="translator">
          <persName xml:id="pfeffer">
            <surname>Niels</surname>
            <forename>Pfeffer</forename>
          </persName>
        </editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
          <persName>
            <surname>Niels</surname>
            <forename>Pfeffer</forename>
          </persName>
        </publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
            <p>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is an original digital text.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="0" type="chapter">
      <head>Annotations.</head>
      <div n="1">
        <head>§. 1.</head>
        <p>
          Since other keys seem to be made for lamenting, for laughing,
          for rejoicing, for devotion, and so on, it almost seems as if
          this one is especially suitable for playing and joking. 
          A violinist will be very pleased to see it, and will find much
          that agrees with his instrument; and he who is capable of the
          flute must hold this key in high esteem, because it is one of
          the most convenient to give it its right strength. But whether an
          oboe or bassoon will also be satisfied with it is doubtful. 
          However, since it must not matter to our thorogh-bass player
          from which key he plays, because one tangent does not require a
          stronger finger than the other, let us rather go through this
          example a little than dwell longer on the character of the key.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="2">
        <head>§. 2.</head>
        <p xml:id="p2-1" facs="#facsZone-p2-1">
          Now, one would like to see the
          <ref target="#measure-0000001591287003 #measure-0000000183024625">
            first two measures
          </ref> played
          quite simply, so that the main theme would come out distinctly
          in accordance with the saying founded in nature and reason, that
          <hi rendition="#b">all beginnings must be simple, plain and clear.</hi>
          With simple playing it is mainly demanded that to each of the six notes
          in the said bars, only one note is played before or on the note with the right hand,
          whereby it must be remembered that playing before refers to the rest.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="3">
        <head>§. 3.</head>
        <p>
          The three following measures are played with the figures in the most exact manner,
          and on each eighth note, the appropriate one is struck; however, in the last
          measure of these three, one must be careful not to take the usual 2 together with the 4+
          since it would not be possible without a mistake, but instead play again the octave
          which is already in the hand, then such a movement will sound completely strange because of the 4+.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="4">
        <head>§. 4.</head>
        <p>
          As for the 6th, 7th and half of the 8th measure,
          one can take a little more liberty and not only
          play them with a doubled octave in the left hand,
          but also play in the right hand three times on six notes
          whatever is in the hands or what is figured.
          The rest of the eighth bar and the ninth measure have their own paths.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="5">
        <head>§. 5.</head>
        <p>
          The fifteenth measure already gives because of the simple notes
          consideration and opportunity to take up the
          main subject in the right hand at will (not that it must be even),
          with the very notes with which the beginning was made;
          however, in such a way that the left hand, as was said once and for all,
          does not forget to play in full voice at the same time: so that
          even when playing alone the quality of the thorough-bass is not
          suspended, but only embellished, as has already been amply
          reminded above in various places.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="6">
        <head>§. 6.</head>
        <p>
          In the 11th bar, the right hand may continue
          with thirds as it began, and the bass can also
          be played double, but it must not be forgotten
          that the right hand must be played full-voiced on
          every first note of the related ones.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="7">
        <head>§. 7.</head>
        <p>
          When one comes to the 12th, 13th and 14th measure,
          one recovers a little and does as one pleases –
          or nothing but what is written. In the 15th and 16th measure
          however, one will already see that the right hand may again
          have to do something, but it will be at the
          beginning, which must be done starting with the d, and
          then everything will follow according to the subject
          in thirds with the bass, whose beats must all be in full voice.
          Otherwise, nothing more is to be remembered until the end of
          the first part, except that the three-tailed notes in the right hand are also in thirds. 
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="8">
        <head>§. 8.</head>
        <p>
          That the other part now seems to begin a new subject is done
          out of love for variety, and each note may be given its proper chord,
          also taking the bass as strongly as possible, which makes a good
          effect especially on the C-sharp and the chromatic notes. 
          
          The six ascending notes in the second bar, as well as the six
          descending notes in the fourth and fifth measure are to be excluded
          from the restriking, and are to be made to sound distinctly in octaves.
          Then the bass takes up the first main subject again and continues with
          it according to the instructions above.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="9">
        <head>§. 9.</head>
        <p>
          In the ninth bar of the other part, it is again played rigidly across the entire
          keyboard to every note; in the last half, however, the right hand can apply
          a soothing manner that is similar to the main subject, which will show a
          student and ponderer the nature of the movement itself: and thus it is
          correct until the end of the thirteenth measure, where the first subject again appears,
          almost as it was in the sixth and following bars of the first part,
          for which reason one may only consult the above and follow the annotation made exactly.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div n="10">
        <head>§. 10.</head>
        <p>
          In the last half of the 16th measure, a small invention
          is to be added with the right hand on the same beat as in
          the tenth bar of the first part; however, the rest of what
          is required must also be taken into consideration up to the
          18th bar, and can then, only as everything stands, be continued:
          whereby, however, the 9. 7. 2. that appears last should never be
          allowed to be mistaken, because it is the chord that just preceded,
          and by which the 6⃥ again becomes pious and good.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>