<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/basisformat_customized.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="part">Mattheson: Der Ober-Classe vierundzwantzigstes Probstück (english translation, excerpts)</title>
        <editor role="translator">
          <persName xml:id="pfeffer">
            <surname>Pfeffer</surname>
            <forename>Niels</forename>
          </persName>
        </editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
          <persName>
            <surname>Pfeffer</surname>
            <forename>Niels</forename>
          </persName>
        </publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
            <p>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is an original digital text.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="0" type="chapter">
        <div n="1">
          <head>§. 1-30.</head>
          <p>
            [omitted]
            <note type="editorial" resp="#pfeffer">
              In these paragraphs Mattheson is mostly concerned about the notation
              of chromatic notes and new chromatic keyboards instruments
              and comments on his long-lasting public dissent with Gottfried Benjamin Hancke. 
              Only the paragraph relevant for the understanding of the Probstück 
              has been translated here (§. 31).
            </note>
          </p>
        </div>

        <div n="2">
          <head>§. 31.</head>
          <p>
            What should be mentioned in our last Probstück is little,
            and mostly concerns the fact that the eighth notes, of which three
            belong to a quarter note, play alone, and to the first
            of them one plays only what is appropriate or figured.
            Circumstances do not yet permit the display of much artistry in such keys;
            nevertheless, at the cadences, namely in the
            <ref target="#measure-0000000102124254 #measure-0000001858057008 #measure-0000001066470152">5th, 16th, and 35th measure</ref>,
            something arpeggiated might be gracefully added.
            However, like all such embellishments and ornaments throughout,
            I do not want to consider it as a necessity for an ordinary thorough-bass,
            but rather as a pleasant and decent addition at a Probe, during practice,
            and on longed-for opportunity, because I completely agree with
            St. Lambert in this place, where he says: 
            If the basses are not overloaded with many notes, but, according
            to the player's sense, drag and hesitate too much, he may well
            add other notes and play more figures; as long as he
            is certain that his additions do not bring any disadvantage
            to the melody, but especially to the singing voice.
            For the thorough bass is ordained for nothing other
            than to assist the singer, but not to hinder or distort
            his efforts by untimely ringing. 
            There are people who think so highly of themselves that they
            believe a whole concert of virtuosos is hardly worthy of them,
            and therefore make it quite sour for themselves to stand out
            before all the others.
            These organists clutter their basses with many crooked leaps,
            embellish everything back and front, and add a hundred kinds
            of things that are perhaps very beautiful in and of themselves,
            but nevertheless come at an inappropriate time and are very
            harmful to the concert, in that they serve nothing else than
            to testify to the artistic thirst for glory and vanity of the player. 
            Whoever therefore plays in a concert must do it in such a way
            that he brings honor and pleasure to the whole group, but
            not that he alone may win the prize. For if each one plays
            only for himself and for his own sake, it is no longer a concert. 
          </p>
        </div>

        <div n="3">
          <head>§. 32-33.</head>
          <p>
            [omitted]
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
